<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The perfection of Scripture stated, and its sufficiency argued in a sermon preached at the publick commencement at Cambridge, Sunday July iv, 1697 / by George Stanhope ...</title>
            <author>Stanhope, George, 1660-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16475</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13153377</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13153377</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 751:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The perfection of Scripture stated, and its sufficiency argued in a sermon preached at the publick commencement at Cambridge, Sunday July iv, 1697 / by George Stanhope ...</title>
                  <author>Stanhope, George, 1660-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Sare ..., and Matt. Wotton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Half title: Dr. Stanhope's sermon at the commencement at Cambridge.</note>
                  <note>Running title: A sermon preach'd at the commencement at Cambridge.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 2nd, III, 16, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Evidences, authority, etc.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98120:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Perfection of Scripture STATED, And Its SUFFICIENCY ARGUED; IN A SERMON PREACHED at the Publick Commencement AT <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi> SUNDAY <hi>July</hi> iv. 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE STANHOPE,</hi> D.D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty, and late Fellow of <hi>King's College.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd at the Deſire of the Reverend the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, the Divinity-Profeſſors, and Other Heads of Colleges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Sare,</hi> at <hi>Gray's-Inn-Gate</hi> in <hi>Holborn;</hi> and <hi>Matt. Wotton,</hi> at the <hi>Three Daggers</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:98120:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98120:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>II. TIMOTH. iii 16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs:</p>
                  <p>That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle having had occaſion in the <hi>fifteenth</hi> Verſe to mention the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, under that general Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, of being <hi>able to make</hi> Timothy <hi>wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> thought fit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large ſomewhat more upon ſo glorious a Subject, and to give this particular and very magnificent Commendation of them, which is contained in the Words now read to you.</p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding whereof, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Argument comprehended under them in its true Light, permit me briefly to premiſe a few Obſervations, with regard to the Expreſſions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe relates to the Subject-Matter of the Aſſertion, <hi>All Scripture;</hi> where, I need not tell you, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> by <hi>Scripture</hi> meant thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98120:3"/>Writings, which were generally received and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced in the Church of God, as authentick Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications of his good Pleaſure. Such were the Books of the Old Teſtament, acknowledged to come from Heaven by the Mouth and Miniſtry of the Prophets; and theſe ſeem to have been the Scriptures which <hi>Timothy</hi> is ſaid <hi>to have known from a child.</hi> (<hi>v.</hi> 15.) And ſuch likewiſe were thoſe of the New Teſtament then extant, which (if we attend to the
<note n="*" place="margin">Ann. Chr. LXVII. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. XIII. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Pearſon. Ceſtr. in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Paulin.</note> Time of ſending this Epiſtle) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, indeed moſt, except the Writings of St. <hi>John,</hi> ſeem to have been.</p>
            <p>And therefore
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>So</hi> Sculte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in locum: Chemnitius Exam. Conc Trident. P. I. cap. 1. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard. Loc. Commun. de Sacr. Script. cap. XVIII. p. 147.</note> Learned Perſons have taken Theſe into the account, and thought St. <hi>Paul</hi> very properly to intimate, that They alſo were equally worthy of <hi>Timothy</hi>'s ſtudy; of the ſame mighty Benefit and Uſe, and ſuch as carried the ſame ſtamp of a Divine Authority, with thoſe of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, to which Men paid ſo profound and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Reſpect.</p>
            <p>But then
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <p>Nomen Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdum Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalitatem ſignificat, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdum Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritatem —Ita hic <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> idem eſt quod <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, adeóque rectè vertitur <hi>Tota Scriptura. Scultet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qui noſtram Interpretationem reſpuunt, obtendunt non dici <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſed <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Sed nec ſi ſequaris Interpretationem noſtram opus crit Articulo. Vox enim <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> nonnunquam etiam ſine Articulo, ſine Adjectivo, ſumitur Antonomaſticè, ut <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Jac. Cappell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Si <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſumas vocem <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; vocem <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vertas <hi>omnis,</hi> in caſſes indues te, ex quibus vix te poſſis expedire. Quaſi vel minimus Scripturae Sacrae verſus habeat omnes hos uſus quos hic deſcribit Apoſtolus. <hi>Jac. Cappell.</hi> Vide quae Scultetus ad locum &amp; Gerhard. è Bellarmino depromptis reſpondent. Loc. Comm. Part. I. Cap. 18. de Sacr. Script. p. 146, 147.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>All Scripture</hi> is to be underſtood, (as the Schools ſpeak) not in a Diſtributive, but a Collective Senſe; <hi>that is,</hi> We muſt interpret it of the whole Body of Scripture taken together and in the groſs, and not of each particular Paſſage to be met with there. The firſt Clauſe of the Text in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98120:3"/>is true even in this more rigid Conſtruction, and an equal neceſſity of the Writers being led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth, and ſecured from all Errour, ſeems to lie upon every part of a Book intended for the Guide of Souls. But moſt aſſuredly it is neither True, nor Neceſſary, nor ſo much as Poſſible, that each particular Paſſage ſhould be of that general Profit and Perfection, and ſerve the ſeveral Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes ſpecified in my Text. And This I take to be ſo plain and obvious, that nothing could excuſe the mention of it, had not ſome Writers of great and very boaſted Name, been content to ſtoop to ſo poor a ſhift as That of alledging againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Opinion concerning the Perfection of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, That this Text to <hi>Timothy</hi> either proves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all in favour of it, or it proves a great deal too much: as making every Book, and every Period, a perfect Rule of Faith and Life; by ſaying that <hi>All Scripture</hi> is thus inſpired and thus exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profitable.</p>
            <p>To theſe Scriptures thus conſidered, our Apoſtle gives <hi>two</hi> Noble Commendations; <hi>Firſt,</hi> That of their Divine Original, <hi>All Scripture is given by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of God. Secondly,</hi> That of their general Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. And This again is farther illuſtrated, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancing, <hi>Firſt,</hi> in the ſeveral Particulars, to which that Uſefulneſs extends, The <hi>Scripture is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs. Secondly,</hi> By declaring the degree of this Uſefulneſs, and the Efficacy of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures in thoſe reſpects, for that by their means the <hi>man of God</hi> is capable of becoming <hi>perfect,</hi> and <hi>throughly furniſhed unto all good works.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98120:4"/>
            <p>By the <hi>Man of God,</hi> the matter is not great whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we underſtand, (with
<note n="*" place="margin">Cajetan. Chemnitius. Hemingius. Vatablus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalio.</note> ſome Interpreters) Every good Chriſtian, whoſe Heart and Life is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to the Service and Obedience of God; Or whether (with
<note n="†" place="margin">Scultetus. Grotius. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard. &amp;c.</note> Others,) the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church; ſuch as <hi>Timothy</hi> himſelf was, and who being dedicated and retaining to God in a more peculiar manner, have a Title to this Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter diſtinct from the reſt of Mankind. For in both ſenſes the Argument comes all to One. Since what the Paſtors are bound to teach, the ſame their Flocks are bound to know, and believe, and do: So that this is but One thing conſidered under different reſpects. And therefore what is ſufficient or defective for a Rule to Men in One of theſe Capacities, muſt conſequently be in proportion ſo to Men in the Other.</p>
            <p>Once more. That the Scripture is a ſufficient Supply for all the Neceſſities of this kind, the Apoſtle declares, by ſaying, <hi>That the man of God may be perfected</hi> by it, and <hi>throughly furniſhed to every good work.</hi> For That cannot be <hi>perfect</hi> which wants any of its ſubſtantial Parts, nor is He <hi>throughly furniſhed</hi> who is ſtill under a neceſſity of ſeeking Supplies elſewhere.</p>
            <p>The Text in all this Latitude, miniſters much more Matter of Diſcourſe, than either the Time or Your Patience can allow to be handled diſtinctly. And therefore omitting wholly that firſt Part, which concerns the Divine Original of Scripture; as leſs ſuitable, and I hope the leſs needful for this Mixt Audience; I beg Leave to confine my ſelf to the Latter, which the Church of <hi>England,</hi> our Wiſe and Holy Mother, hath
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98120:4"/>thus expreſt in her Sixth Article of Religion: <hi>The Holy Scripture containeth all Things neceſſary to Salvation, ſo that whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any Man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> If this be once acknowledged for Truth, I do not ſee how any Man ſo perſuaded, can deny the Scripture's Ability <hi>of making us Wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation,</hi> and being a Compleat Guide in Points of Faith and Manners. And ſuch I ſhall endeavour to prove it, by ſhewing,</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> What manner of Perfection that is, which Men ought to attribute to Scripture, and are warranted to expect from it.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> What general Arguments we have to ground this Opinion upon; and</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How the Scripture anſwers this Character in thoſe particular Inſtances mention'd by my Text.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt.</hi> I am to conſider, What manner or ſort of Perfection that is, which we are allowed to attribute to, and to expect from the Scriptures. And This deſerves to be the more heedfully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to, becauſe the Liberty Some have taken of impoſing other Guides and Rules, beſides the Scripture; and the imprudent Zeal of Others, who profeſs to follow this in every Thing, and hang upon the Word and Letter of Scripture; have given Birth to many extravagant Opinions, and greatly diſturb'd Chriſtianity and good Order.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98120:5"/>
            <p>Now, Scripture being in the Nature of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium or Inſtrument directed to a certain End, the beſt and moſt regular Way of coming to a right Underſtanding in this Matter, will be to take a ſhort View of the Deſign of Scripture, and what Degree of Perfection is neceſſary to anſwer that Deſign. Or to keep cloſe to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Expreſſion, <hi>v.</hi> 15. To examine what is meant by <hi>Salvation,</hi> and what is requiſite to qualifie us for, and make us <hi>Wiſe unto Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Salvation is but another Word for that Eternal Happineſs, which God hath appointed to be the Ultimate and Chief Good of Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; This Happineſs is propoſed not as our Fate, but as our Reward; and ſince every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſuppoſes ſome Works in Conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Recompence is beſtowed, it implyes, that Men muſt contribute ſomething to their own Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and cannot reaſonably hope to obtain it, without attending to thoſe Conditions, upon the performance of which the Reward is ſuſpended. It implies farther, that the Notices of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and the Right of appointing them, muſt come from, and are Originally lodged in Him, who propoſes and promiſes that Recompence. And, if our Expectations and Deſires of this Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py State, be Natural and Univerſal, it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from hence too, that Nature furniſhes Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind with ſome ſort of Means and Abilities, as well as Inclinations, to aſpire after it: For the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of the Creator is moſt eminently ſeen in This; that he deludes none of his Creatures with vain Expectations, nor infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes any ſuch Deſires into them, as muſt of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98120:5"/>be diſappointed. Theſe Abilities I take to have been given in thoſe general Notions of Good and Evil, impreſt upon the Mind of Man, at his Firſt Creation.
<note place="margin">Rom. II. 13, 14, 15.</note> With regard to which St. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions a Law written in the Hearts of Thoſe, to whom the written Law was not imparted. He obſerves the ſame pleaſing Tranſports, the ſame melancholy Miſgivings to riſe in their Breaſts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as Their Conſciences accuſe, or excuſe them: He declares, that in the Laſt Great Day of Account, They ſhall be judged upon this Iſſue. Since then, there was a Time, when Man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed no written Word at all; ſince after ſome Parts of the World were bleſt with ſuch Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet Others were unfortunate in the Want of it; Since even Thoſe who had it not, were yet Accountable for their Actions, The Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is Plain and Neceſſary; that the Holy Scriptures are not the Only Method whereby God hath been pleaſed to inform Men of their Duty; They were not the Firſt, they were not the Univerſal, and conſequently not the ſole and perpetual Inſtrument of all our Privileges, and all our Obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whatever hopes Men could by Nature have, theſe had no other Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than a juſt and punctual Performance; and therefore Sin quite altered the Caſe, and made a farther Revelation neceſſary. What St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays elſewhere of the Jewiſh Law, may with great Truth, and in a very good Senſe, be affirmed of <hi>All Scripture,</hi> that it was <hi>added becauſe of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</hi> To Perſons thus concluded under For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, no Expectation juſtly could be cheriſhed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98120:6"/>no Succour or ſolid Comfort could ariſe, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than from God's expreſs Declaration, that he would condeſcend to freſh Conditions, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit us to another and better Covenant, ſuch as our laps'd and guilty State would bear. Hence, ſure it is, that the preſent Methods of Salvation, are term'd, <hi>The Secret of the Lord, The Myſtery of our Redemption,</hi> and the like; becauſe Theſe are ſome of the the unſearchable Dephts of infinite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, ſuch as no Humane Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe could penetrate into, no natural Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions could infer: And, becauſe God was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Free in this whole Matter, he let Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Knowledge of it, by ſuch gradual Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, as himſelf ſaw fit; and ſuch as dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and degenerate Minds were capable of. This is the ſhining Ray then darted from above, to give our Souls once more the chearing Proſpect of Bliſs Divine and Love Incomprehenſible. 'Tis thus we are ſupported and aſſured, that our Judge is not Irreconcileable, that our Sickneſſes are not yet unto Death, provided We will lend a help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hand, and not obſtruct our own Recovery. But ſtill all this was not a new Creation, but a Cure; and therefore, like Other Remedies, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed only, ſo far as the Diſeaſe required: In other Reſpects, it left Men as it found them, and the Benefits of it will be ſtill more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly underſtood, if we be Diligent to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly.</hi> That God in all his Dealings with Mandkind does not act ſo much in Proportion to his Own Fulneſs, as to Our Wants. And therefore we have Reaſon to look upon thoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98120:6"/>Diſcoveries of his Will to be Perfect, which revealed, not all that could be revealed, but all that Men had Occaſion for. In this Senſe the more ſparing Revelations heretofore were perfect in their Kind, though in Degree and Meaſure ſhort of Ours. The Impreſſions of Reaſon at Man's Firſt Creation, were ſo in ſome Senſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that State needed no more. So were the Private and Perſonal Diſcoveries after the Fall, the Jewiſh Law and Predictions of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets afterwards, Each of which had their Day, and proper Seaſon; as the Manifeſtations of the Goſpel have Theirs Now, which are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the laſt concluding Diſpenſation, that which completes, confirms, and cloſe, up all the reſt. In judging therefore the Perfection of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, we muſt ever attend to the Deſign it ſerves, and its Sufficiency to compaſs that Deſign. For Example: In the Hiſtorical Part, we are not to expect a full and juſt Relation of all that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the World at that Time; no nor of all that happened to that People, of whoſe Affairs it more profeſſedly treats; a Competent Quantity of the main and moſt ſignificant Paſſages will ſerve the turn; ſuch as draw down a juſt Account of our Bleſſed Saviour, and wherein the Law and Polity of the Jews, were Types of Him, or of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church.</p>
            <p>So again, The Prophecies do not foretell all that ſhould happen under the Goſpel, nor every Thing to be done by our Lord himſelf; but are contented with drawing the Principal Lines, and giving Repreſentations, and Characters, ſo like, and lively, as when the Son of God ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Fleſh, and Events came to be compared
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98120:7"/>with Predictions, might render Men exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to blame, if they did not accept and regard That Perſon, as the promiſed Meſſias, in whom thoſe Deſcriptions ſo exactly center'd. Nay, even in the Goſpel it ſelf, St. <hi>John</hi> makes no Difficulty to own, that a World of remarkable and wonderful Things done by Chriſt, are not, however, left upon Record; but that Enough are left to build Men's Faith upon. Now, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deny'd, but the All-wiſe God could, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der each of thoſe Periods, have inſpired the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pen-Men with all that are omitted; or that he could, if he had pleaſed, have made but One Period, and revealed all together; But when he did not ſo, we have Reaſon to conclude, that the Meaſure of his Revelations is directed by the End of them; that he intended not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for a Repoſitory of all Truths, in the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and moſt comprehenſive Senſe of the Word, But of <hi>all</hi> which were needful <hi>to make Men wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> ſuch as their preſent Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces required, and what he intended they ſhould be accountable for. And, as he would not be Niggardly in theſe Communications, ſo neither was he Profuſe: Nay, from hence I argue,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That even all Truths, which may have any Tendency to direct Men in their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are not particularly and expreſly to be found there; nor is it all neceſſary, or indeed, (Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly ſpeaking) poſſible, that they ſhould. And This directly meets with an Opinion, unhappy in it's Conſequences, but entertained, (it is to be hoped) out of an honeſt Zeal and well-meant Reverence for theſe Bleſſed Writings. That I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98120:7"/>mean of <hi>Mens not being allowed to do any thing, for which ſome expreſs Command, or Warrant, or at leaſt Example may not be produced out of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> I cannot now ſtand to ſhew the Danger and Uncertainty of governing our Lives by the Examples even of Good Men; but ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prove the unreaſonableneſs of this Rule in general, and to diſengage Men from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſad Suſpenſes and Snares, which it is apt to bring unwary Conſciences under, by theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let it be remembred, that our Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to obey the Scriptures, does not ariſe from their being Written, but from their being the Diſcoveries of God's Will and our Duty. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, Whatever comes to my Knowledge as his Pleaſure concerning me, hath the ſame bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power upon my Conſcience, be the Method of making it ſo known to me what it will. The Authority of the Law-Giver, and the ſufficient Promulging of the Law: Theſe are the Things, that induce the Obligation to Obedience; And therefore, if God, who is the abſolute and only Maſter of my Conſcience, have ſeveral ways of ſignifying his Pleaſure, the particular Manner of doing it is accidental and foreign to this Binding Power, and makes not the leaſt Difference in my Engagement to Submiſſion and Obedience.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Secondly,</hi> We may be ſatisfy'd, that God not only did formerly, but that he does ſtill uſe other Methods of manifeſting his Will, beſides that of the written Word. There have been Times and Perſons that knew no other Law but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; And when God added a brighter Candle,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98120:8"/>he did not put out the old one, or forbid us to walk by it's Light, ſo far as that is able to direct us. The very Divine Authority of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and the Being of the God from whence that Authority is derived, are Principles ariſing from Common Reaſon. And how abſurd would it be to allow no Standard of Truth in Religion, no Rule of Behaviour, but Scripture, when the Two Fundamental Truths of all Religion muſt be made out to us from other Principles, and cannot with any Propriety of arguing be fetched from Scripture it ſelf?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The very Temper and Compoſition of Scripture is ſuch, as neceſſarily refers us to ſome other Rule: For This is a Syſtem of mixed and very different Duties. Some of Eternal and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Obligation, Others Occaſional and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, Limited to Times and Circumſtances; and when Thoſe Occaſions and Circumſtances ceaſed, the Matter of the Command was loſt, and the whole Reaſon and Force of it ſunk of courſe. This is obſervable, more eſpecially in the Jewiſh Diſpenſation, but it is likewiſe true in ſundry other Caſes. Now theſe Things being oftentimes delivered promiſcuouſly and in general Terms, Men muſt of neceſſity have Recourſe to ſome other Rule, to diſtinguiſh, and guide them in making the juſt Differences between the one and the other Sort. And This is what Equity and the Reaſon of the Thing muſt do, where the Word of God it ſelf hath made no expreſs Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Scriptures as a Rule of Faith and Life, do not concern us, juſt as the Words and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98120:8"/>Syllables are ſet down there; but according to the true Senſe, and Rational Meaning of the Text. And in Order to juſt Reſolutions of this kind, many Qualifications are requiſite; A Mind truly Honeſt, and reſign'd to the Will of God, ſincere and unprejudiced; the being not only Content, but Deſirous to learn; and ready to retract Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and reform Vices, when upon a Fair Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination they ſhall appear to be ſuch. To This we muſt add Diligence, and Care, and Skill; ſuch as may enable Men to compare, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile, and form a Judgment out of, the Scriptures; to conſider the Contexts, the Occaſions, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, the Genius of the Countries, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties of Languages, and to fix upon ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious Interpretations from hence, as may never ſet one Scripture at Variance with another. And where theſe Qualifications are not to be had, there a meek and quiet Spirit, an orderly Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to honeſt and better Judgments, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during to be Ignorant in Matters above one's Reach. Now, all this is the Work of a Man's own underſtanding and Will, aſſiſted by God's Grace; and all ſo neceſſary, that without ſuch Application and Appeals to fair unbyaſs'd Reaſon, the very Word of God it ſelf may miſguide and prove a Snare to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Nature of Humane Actions puts it out of diſpute, that the Scriptures alone can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be a full and perfect Direction, in Point of Duty: For the Circumſtances of Human Life are infinite, and depend upon a multitude of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, not to be foreſeen, and conſequently not to be provided againſt. Hence Laws muſt run
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98120:9"/>in general Terms, and ſometimes the Intent of the Law is beſt fulfilled, by going counter to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it. In all ſuch Caſes therefore Reaſon and Honeſty muſt guide us to the fitneſs of the thing, and great Scope is neceſſarily left to Equity and Diſcretion. I allow indeed, that God, who hath contented himſelf with general Rules, could have deſcribed all the Accidents and Circumſtances, which he cannot but foreſee and know exactly. But there is no Reaſon why he ſhould, and a great deal why he ſhould not. 'Tis much better, that he hath left us to draw general Rules into parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Practice, and put us upon the Tryal of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this fairly; of diſcharging a Good Conſcience in poſitive Obedience, where he hath determined things to Moral Good or Evil; and of following the Meaſures of Integrity and Expediency, where he hath left them indifferent and at large.</p>
            <p>The Summ then of this <hi>Firſt</hi> Head may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily drawn together, within the Compaſs of theſe few ſhort Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> As to the Myſteries and Doctrines pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Chriſtian Faith, ſuch as, The Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Satisfaction of our Bleſſed Saviour, the Juſtification of Sinners by Faith, the Aſſiſtances of the Holy Spirit, the Trinity of Perſons in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, (which I make no Scruple to call a neceſſary and diſtinguiſhing Doctrine of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion) In theſe the Scriptures are our ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and only Rule, For They are Branches of a New Covenant, Revelations of Stupendous and Important Concern, ſetting forth Free Acts of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; ſuch as depended upon no neceſſary Cauſes in Nature; ſuch as concern'd not Man in his primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98120:9"/>State; and therefore not within the Ken of Reaſon. Theſe could come only from God, and upon Him we are therefore to depend entirely for them. So that when there is ſufficient Evidence of His having delivered any Matters of this kind, All the reſt is to be taken upon content; and his Truth and Infinite Wiſdom are a juſt Foundation of our Belief, how far ſoever the Matter revealed may exceed our Comprehenſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> In Matters of Practice the Scripture is our Supreme, though not our only Rule. Thoſe things which Reaſon and Nature teach, This enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and refines upon, and oftentimes confirms with a freſh Sanction. It exalts our Vertues, and directs us to proceed upon nobler Principles; teaches ſome Duties not to be known without it, gives clearer Convictions of ſuch as were known imperfectly; leads us to Ends above nature, furniſhes Means above the Powers of Nature; propoſes Rewards Heavenly and Divine, and helps us to do more than mere Men by their own diſcourſe could ever have done. So that Revelation does not quench the Light of Nature, but adds freſh oil, and makes it burn the brighter; And by being more perfect, helping our dimneſs and dark ſight, and taking place above all other Authorities, it is properly ſtyled by <hi>David, A candle to our feet, and a lantern to our paths,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> cxix. 105.) So that whatever this Word teaches, which we might otherwiſe have known, has a double tye upon us; and That which either Want of Underſtanding or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mind would have kept us in ignorance of, when found here, is to be received with Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reverence, as an inviolable Law, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98120:10"/>Fleſh and Senſe, and Worldly Wiſdom may ſuggeſt or object to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Perfection of Scripture does not confine it ſelf to ſuch Matters of Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice as are abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, but it is liberal and well fraught with excellent Rules both for improving our Knowledge, and adorning our Profeſſion. It conſults the Beauty and Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, as well as the Life and Being of Chriſtianity. It directs the ſhining of our Light, and the winning over others by our Prudence and Good Example; and leaves us general Hints, the Efficacy of which will depend upon the Honeſty and Diſcretion of particular: Applications to our own perſonal Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies and Conditions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There are many Caſes, where Scripture can have nothing at all to do, except by very remote Conſequences, and ſo far only as is implied in the foregoing Particular. Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Actions of Humane Life there are, ſo trivial, as ſcarde to deſerve the deliberation of a ſingle Thought. And to expect Laws and Deciſions from Almighty God in things of no Importance, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Good or Evil, were to bring his Majeſty into Contempt; and therefore here Diſcretion is our only Guide. In ſhort, and to conclude this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: The Written Word of God is to be eſteemed Sufficient and Perfect; but This is to be underſtood of having the Sufficiency of Means to the End; and what may ſerve the Purpoſes to which it was ordained. The Perfection is that of an Inſtrument, but then This, like all other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, requires an honeſt, skilful, and diligent Hand to manage and apply it Succeſsfully. And it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98120:10"/>is no Diſparagement to the Scripture's Character, that Some by neglecting, and Others by abuſing it, ſtill want that Saving Wiſdom it might give; Nor does it at all take off from the Perfection of this Rule, that ſome Caſes are ſo plain and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as not to need its particular Directions, and that Others are of ſo little moment, as not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Way being thus made plain, by rightly Stating the Perfection of Scripture, let us now proceed to the <hi>Second</hi> Part of our Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is, To inſtance in ſome general Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which the Proteſtant Opinion of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture's Sufficiency, may very reaſonably alledge for its ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now in order to make Scripture a Competent Guide in the Caſes that properly concern it, <hi>Two</hi> things only are neeeſſary; That it be Sufficiently particular and expreſs, and that it be plain and intelligible. That as much be delivered there as the occaſion requires, and, That it be delivered in ſuch a manner, as that Men may improve by it, and attain to the Knowledge of it. Both which, to any Man who conſiders the Uſes of Scripture, appear to be ſo neceſſarily required, and ſo greatly related to, that the ſame General Arguments will prove both, and theſe that follow, (if I miſtake not) may contribute ſomething toward it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Conſideration of the Author. Every Imperfection in the Effect is owing to ſome Failure in the Cauſe, a want of Power if it be a Neceſſary Cauſe, or a Want of Will if it be a Sufficient and Free Cauſe. There was therefore excellent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98120:11"/>why St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould begin his Character of the Scripture's Perfection, with an Account of its being <hi>given by inſpiration of God;</hi> This Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on carrying in it a very Significant Argument to enforce what follows. For where indeed ſhould we expect Perfection, if not from Him, who is the Source and Summ of all Perfection? He whoſe Power and Wiſdom are infinite, was moſt likely to impreſs upon his own Ordinances ſuch Marks of Excellency, as might diſtinguiſh them plainly, and convince the World they were His, by being worthy of Him: And He, whoſe Goodneſs and Mercy are the Eminent ſhining Attributes of the Divinity, might reaſonably be preſumed to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe that Power and Wiſdom, when an occaſion ſo important as the Salvation of a whole World call'd for it. His own mere Bounty put him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the myſterious Work of our Redemption, and can we ſuppoſe, that the very Terms upon which the Succeſs and Efficacy of that Work depends, are not ſufficiently ſtated and made known?</p>
            <p>We are told indeed, no Writing can be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Rule, becauſe capable of different Couſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that ſome Living Interpreter is neceſſary, upon whoſe Senſe we may ſecurely rely: But what Underſtanding is ſo ſhort, as not to ſee the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Argument? For is any thing ſpoken which might not be written? and would not the ſame words when written, continue to be as full, as clear, as plain and diſtinct, as when ſpoken on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Is not any Man's diſcourſe from his Tongue as liable to be wreſted and perverted, as that from his Pen? If then that living Interpreter (whoever he be) might have his Senſe committed to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98120:11"/>and if that Senſe when not written, lies open to the ſame danger of being miſunderſtood, as when it is written, then a written Word may be as plain and ſufficient a Rule as an Oral one. And if Almighty God could expreſs himſelf as plainly and clearly as Man, (which to deny were moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and impious) then nothing hinders, why the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of the Holy Ghoſt written in the Bible, might not be as ſafe, as full, as intelligible a Direction, as any Interpretations, or Decrees, compoſed by any living Perſons, or Society of Perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. They might be ſo, I ſay, which proves a Written Rule capable of equal Perfection with an Oral one. And as the Nature of the thing ſhews it capable, ſo the Goodneſs of God gives juſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of its actually being ſo. We are able in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to give ſome Account, why Humane Laws ſhould be obſcure; Men may not be always happy in their Expreſſions, or they may leave them intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and dark, and ſtudiouſly contrive ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Ambiguities: But God hath neither Frailty nor Intereſt to diſpoſe him thus. He ſpeaks on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be underſtood; and what is ſpoken ſo as not to be underſtood, is ſo far forth as if not ſpoke at all. To leave Men in darkneſs and diſtreſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed with Helps, the want of which muſt be their Eternal Ruine, this is what we think but ill agrees with the kind Inclinations he hath other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expreſs'd for our Happineſs. And this will appear yet more improbable, if we conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What the particular Matter is, of which the Scriptures chiefly conſiſt, and are intended to inſtruct us in. This I have already ſaid is <hi>The Second Covenant</hi> with fallen Man; and that what
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98120:12"/>other things are added there, are with Subſervience to this Great deſign. And can we ſuppoſe that theſe Great Charters and Indentures are drawn imperfectly? In other Sciences there may be many Common Principles and Helps deriv'd from abroad; and theſe are ſuch as ſhine in ſome meaſure by each other's Light. But the Doctrines and Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Chriſtianity are not in the power of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Art to define; we have no further inſight here, than what the Light from Heaven directs us to; and whatever of this kind God hath not made known to us, we are condemned to Doubts and Difficulties invincible, and can never bring our ſelves to know it at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Sufficiency and Plainneſs of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture are both of them ſtrongly implied in Faith and Obedience, being made the Conditions of Everlaſting Salvation; and Unbelief and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience threatned with Hell and Damnation, to as many as live under the Knowledge and Light of the Goſpel. For if Belief and Practice muſt bring us to Heaven, then ſure God hath left a Complete Syſtem of all things neceſſary to be believed or done; And if Men ſhall be damned for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and not practiſing, then ſure thoſe Directions are ſufficiently plain: Eſpecially too, if we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that theſe Conditions are not calculated for the Wiſe, or the Learned, or the Great only; but impoſed indifferently upon all Degrees and Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of Men, of what ſize ſoever their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings or their Attainments be. For in regard no Man is capable of Believing or Doing, what he is not capable of knowing the Senſe and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of; it muſt needs follow, that in the Terms
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98120:12"/>of Salvation, God hath deſcended to the Weak and the Common Man; and made that which is neceſſary to All, eaſie and plain to All. The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of <hi>marking what is done amiſs, who,</hi> ſays the <hi>Pſalmiſt, may abide?</hi> But would not the marking and puniſhing what could not but be done amiſs, be a much more inſupportable Extremity? And yet, admitting that Men are condemned to Everlaſting Torments, for failure in that Duty of which God never gave them ſufficient Means of Information, I cannot apprehend, but that this is the Caſe with them. The Force of which Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in general, That God muſt needs have made ſufficient Diſcoveries of his Will, is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly evident, that the only Fault our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries find with us for alledging it, is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining theſe Diſcoveries to Scripture only; to juſtifie which Inference I add in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth</hi> place, That we have no equal Evidence for any other Supplementary Declaration of God's Will, and therefore we have Reaſon to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Scriptures as a full and Sufficient one.
<note place="margin">In his quae apertè in ſcripturâ po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſunt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniuntur illa omnia quae continent Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem moreſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vivendi, ſpem ſcilicet at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Charitatem. <hi>Auguſtin. de Doctrin. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi> Lib. II. Cap. 9.</note> Now, that ſuch Evidence was abſolutely need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, appears from hence, That whatſoever mends and fills up the Meaſure of any other Law, and to which we muſt have our laſt Recourſe and Appeal, does by that Means acquire not only equal, but in ſome ſort a ſuperiour Authority to what went before; and therefore, to be ſure, it ought to have it's own Authority, at leaſt as well confirm'd, as That which it pretends to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Now, the Scriptures command our Aſſent and Obedience, as coming from God, That they came from Him we are aſſured, by their Author's
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98120:13"/>giving Proper and Authentick Teſtimonies of a Commiſſion and Inſpiration truly Divine; That the Miracles in which that Teſtimony conſiſted, were really performed, we have the Report of Enemies as well as Friends to their Doctrine; The Proof of Infinite Converts won over by them, contrary to all the Intereſt and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Fleſh and Blood; and Laſtly, The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring Conſent of the Church Univerſal in all Ages, which alone (all Circumſtances conſider'd) is an Evidence even Credible in it ſelf. 'Till therefore the Advancers of Traditions and an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Guide on the one Hand, and till the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to private Illuminations on the other, can bring equal Evidence for themſelves; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially while they continue the darkeſt Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in all Religion; we are not to be blamed for not admitting them into Competition; and ſhall do better to ſuſpect theſe Pretences of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Enthuſiaſm, and Project; than by admitting them to draw ſuch a meaning upon the Words of this Text, as might eaſily be ſhewed to introduce an inſpired Apoſtle, talking neither good Argument, nor ſo much as Coherent and common Senſe.</p>
            <p>The Summ then of my Second Head is This, That, according to all we can reaſonably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of God, he muſt needs have made ſome Competent Proviſion for Men's underſtanding their Duty; They cannot eſcape eternal Ruine, without the Knowledge of it; This Knowledge, in the Points peculiarly Chriſtian, could come to them by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation only; It does not appear that God hath ſignaliz'd and diſtinguiſh'd any Method or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98120:13"/>Rule of this kind, in ſo eminent a manner, as he hath done the Scriptures; and therefore we have reaſon to believe, and to reſpect the Scriptures, as that competent Proviſion. And now, having gone thro' ſuch general Arguments as ſeem moſt neceſſary, I come to the <hi>Third</hi> and laſt Thing, which is,</p>
            <p n="3">III. To ſhew in particular as briefly as I can, How the Scriptures anſwer this Character, with Regard to the ſeveral Inſtances of their Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs mention'd in the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, The Scripture is <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for Doctrine,</hi> by which is commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, a Declaration of ſuch Truths as are neceſſary to be believed. The Summ of what is requiſite in this Point, conſiſtts of a right In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation concerning God and our ſelves: What He is, and what we are and hope to be; What he hath done for our Sakes, and How we may reap the Benefit of it in our own Perſons, and become acceptable in his Sight. And of this the Scripture gives a large and clear Account. It traces us up to our firſt Head, points to the Rock whence we were hewn; deſcribes our Happy and our Healthful State, tells when, and how, our Innocence was loſt, and ſets forth both the Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the Cure. It preſents us with the lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely Advances towards it, the Perſonal Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to the Patriarchs, The Rites and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, The clearer Predictions, and more refined Precepts of the Prophets, and Theſe accommodated to the ſeveral Stages of the World, and tempered all in ſuch Proportion, as the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſeaſed gathered Strength to digeſt them. At
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98120:14"/>laſt, when the fulneſs of Time was come, and Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ripe for the laſt and moſt perfect Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it ſhews us the Saviour of the World, the Son of God, and in Him all thoſe Shadows and rough imperfect Strokes finiſhed and filled up, all thoſe Prophecies centring together, with marvellous Harmony and Conſent. To Theſe I might add the ſignificant Providences of God to his People, the Jews, whereby St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays they became <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Patterns, and Images of the Chriſtian Age; no leſs than in their Law and Way of Worſhip. I might obſerve the mighty Care and Art of filling every Book with Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of the Meſſiah, his Character, and his Approach, ſometimes by Prophecies aiming direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at him, ſometimes by mix'd and more obſcure Intimations, and thoſe breakings out of the Spirit from other Subjects and Perſons, into Expreſſions too Lofty and Magnificent, to be literally and ſtrictly true of any but of Him. But, which comes nearer Home, here we have our Souls raiſed to higher and juſter Notions of God and Goodneſs; we are taught to worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, a Service moſt ſuitable to the Majeſty of His Nature, and the Dignity of our own: We ſee the Adorable Myſtery of the Son of God in Fleſh and a Human Body, exalted to the Right-Hand of the Majeſty on high, a Perſon truly Divine converſing with Men, courting them to their Happineſſes, preſſing, importuning; nay, which is moſt of all, Dying for Them, that They may live for ever. And whatever myſterious and intricate Paſſages the Scripture may contain, for the Exerciſe, ſhall I ſay, or for the Humiliation of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98120:14"/>Men Wiſe in their own Conceits, yet Theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which make the Hiſtorical Account of our Redemption are related in Circumſtances ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, and yet ſo moving, in Language ſo eaſie, and ſo expreſſive too; that the moſt Scrupulous, if a fair and honeſt, Reader may be ſettled and convinced; and the plaineſt and groſſeſt Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding may be enlightned and edified by them. For whatever Darkneſs and Miſts may now obſcure theſe ſaving Truths, it is not from themſelves or their original Ambiguities, ſo much as from the ſtudied Niceties of Subtil and Deſigning Men; Who, under Pretence of diſtinguiſhing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, have rather confounded and rendred them Unintelligible; and many times diſtinguiſhed away even Truth and Piety it ſelf: But, bleſſed be God we are not utterly at theſe Mens Mercies, for to our Comfort, the Apoſtle obſerves,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Scripture is likewiſe Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for <hi>Reproof;</hi> by which is commonly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Confuting of Errors and corrupt Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which oppoſe or impair the Truth.
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. viii. 20. Matt. xxii. 29. Mar. xii. 24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ſeu ut alii le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſoſt. in Johan. <hi>Hom.</hi> XL.</note> Thus among the Jews, the Law and the Teſtimony was the Touch and Tryal, to which all new Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were to be brought. Thus our Saviour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly attributes the <hi>Sadduces</hi> Error concerning the Reſurrection and a Future State, to their not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures. And to the ſame Purpoſe the Apoſtle here ſends <hi>Timothy</hi> to the Scriptures, as a Defence againſt thoſe Corrupt and Perillous times foretold in the Beginning of this Chapter. The earneſt Exhortations of all the Primitive Fathers, to be much converſant in theſe Holy Books; Their placing all the Miſchief of their Diviſions to the Account of neglecting ſo to do; the ſetting the Two
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98120:15"/>Teſtaments, in the midſt of the Ancient and pureſt Councils, as a common Umpire between all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Parties; and infinite Teſtimonies and Commendations to this purpoſe, ſhew moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, that the Written Word was always look'd upon as the Standard of Doctrine and Faith; That to which all ought to have recourſe, to ſubmit to, and be finally concluded by. Traditionary Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and Infalible Interpreters, had then no place, nor was it requiſite they ever ſhould: For though St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays ſome Scriptures <hi>were wreſted to mens own deſtruction,</hi> yet he acquaints us withal, how they came to be ſo. They were, he ſays, <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and unſtable,</hi> that did it, Men not well prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled, and of a reſtleſs Temper. And if People will come to this Rule with perverſe, unquiet Minds, with a Spirit of Frowardneſs, and Cavil, and Contention, they may, no doubt, confound the cleareſt Things: Beſides (which makes the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection much leſs formidable) St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Paſſages <hi>hard to be underſtood</hi> were principally concerned in this racking of the Senſe. And ſo long as Captious Wits exerciſe upon Theſe only, the Conſequence is not ſo very great. They are the neceſſary Points in which we maintain the Sufficiency of Scripture, and I hope it hath been proved, that what is not full and plain, cannot be neceſſary. If Men would read the Bible with Honeſty and Diligence, with Meekneſs and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, the World would quickly come to a good Agreement in Things requiſite to Salvation; and for the reſt, we may entertain different Notions, and yet all ſides be ſafe and quiet. And would Men but preſerve all that Charity and Good Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which becomes Diſputes of ſmall Importance,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98120:15"/>it would ſignifie but little, whether ſuch Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies were ever agreed or not. When Mens Eternal State is brought into hazard, when the Peace of the Publick, or the Order of the Church is broken, when private Friendſhips ceaſe, and Miſunderſtandings and Bickerings ariſe; Theſe are not the Effects of Difference in Opinion, but of the Vanity and Indiſcretion, the Intemperate Heats, and bitter Zeal of thoſe who differ, and not content to differ only, miſmanage and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtand Matters. In ſhort, <hi>Holding the Faith in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Spirit, and in the Bond of Peace</hi> both, is beſt promoted by Righteouſneſs of Life. And whoever ſhall examine the Riſe and Growth of Hereſies and Schiſms, will find that Craft and not Ignorance hath generally been at the Bottom. Pride and Avarice, and Ambition, Envy and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs, Unreaſonable Pertinaciouſneſs, and a Deſire of Popularity, and in one Word, not ſo much the Want as the Abuſe of Wit; Theſe are the rank Weeds that choak the Good Seed, that make the Word Unfruitful, and ſometimes even enſnaring. And to clear the Soil of theſe Nui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſances muſt be every Man's own Care. In ſhort. God hath done as much for us, as it became him to do; he hath left Neceſſary Truth plain and obvious, he will be gracious to innocent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Ignorance and Miſtakes; and therefore, tho' All may be deceived in unneceſſary Points, yet None ſhall be deceived to his own Hurt and Ruine; Except thoſe who wilfully deceive themſelves, or make it their Buſineſs to pervert and diſturb others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the next Inſtance of the Scripture's Profitableneſs is in <hi>Correction,</hi> that is, according to the common Acceptation of the Word, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98120:16"/>of Manners. And in this indeed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the peculiar Glory of Chriſtianity, that it makes the World better, ſweetens Mens Tempers, purifies their Hearts and Affections, tames their wild Paſſions, and checks thoſe Exorbitancies, which render them Odious to God, Uneaſie to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and Troubleſome to one another. That no Man therefore might have Ignorance to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, this Doctrine, like a Light hung out from Heaven, deſcries the Rocks and Shelves that threaten us with Shipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience. And if it happen, (as God knows it does, and often will even to the Beſt of Men) that we be driven upon theſe Rocks, we are then inſtructed, exhorted, entreated, conjured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover our ſelves by ſpeedy and ſerious Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; to call up all the Powers of Reaſon and Religion; and to quicken us the more, we are told the Dangers of Delay, the ſad Doom of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy and Impenitence. We are kept in Awe even from our ſecret Sins, by the conſtant Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſtrict Obſervation of an All-ſeeing Judge; One from whoſe Thunder no Covert can ſhelter, and from whoſe Eye no Darkneſs can hide us; One that does not only purſue us to our Cloſets and Beds, but unlocks our very Hearts and Reins, and ſees all the Monſters, all the deformed Race of evil Thoughts and Actions, even in their Embryo and crude Conception. Here we have Vice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask'd, and ſhewn in it's Native Deviliſhneſs; as the Blackeſt and baſeſt Thing in it ſelf; the moſt Deceitful in its Appearances, the moſt Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in its Effects. The Mother of Sorrow, and Shame, and Death, that cheats us with Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pleaſures of a Moment, and Satisfactions that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98120:16"/>flee from us in the very Inſtant of ſnatching them; but leaves real and laſting Pains behind, abandons us to all the Horrours of Guilt, and Confuſion, Amazement and Deſpair, ſowes all the Seeds of Diſcord and Diſorder, breaks all Faith, cuts the Bands of Society in ſunder, and after all the Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Mind, Pains of Body, private and publick Miſeries on Earth, plunges Men at laſt into the Bottomleſs Pit; a Place of Vengeance and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Remorſes; the Gnawings of a Worm that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dies, and the Burnings of a Flame never to be quenched. Theſe are the Terrors of the Lord to perſwade Men to be Wiſer, and ſtupid ſure are They, whom theſe will not perſwade.</p>
            <p>Once more, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Scripture is ſaid to be Profitable for <hi>Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs,</hi> that is, The directing us how we may pleaſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like unto God. To this Purpoſe it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes pure and holy Hearts, clean Hands, well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govern'd Paſſions, a ſtrict and watchful Guard againſt Temptation; a Mind eaſie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to Providence, raiſed above the preſent World, and therefore Moderate in its Deſires, and reſerv'd in its Enjoyments. It conſults the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all Conditions, and preſcribes Virtues proper for every Relation and Capacity of Human Life. It invites to the Practice of Theſe, by their own Lovelineſs and Beauty, By the Satisfactions they bring to our Selves, and the Benefit they are of to Others: For if a Gracefulneſs of Behaviour, and perpetual Conſiſtency with a Man's ſelf; if the Eaſe and Tranſport of one's own Mind, and the Commendation of other People; If Health, and Peace, and mutual Happineſs; If the Bleſſings
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98120:17"/>which a Good Life hath a natural Tendency to produce, and thoſe which it gives a Title to, by recommending Men to the more Eſpecial Favour and Protection of God; if the aſpiring to be like Him here, and the Aſſurance of being Eternally Happy with him hereafter: If Theſe, I ſay, have any Charms, (and ſurely Charms they have to all, but loſt and ſtupified Souls) then it muſt be acknowledged, that Men want no ſufficient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in Righteouſneſs, while they enjoy the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Four Topicks reſulting from the moſt uſual Senſe of the Text; but if we inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as ſome do, of <hi>ſtrengthning that which is Weak,</hi> and inſtead of <hi>Correction,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Support to feeble and dejected Minds;</hi> then St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Obſervation to the <hi>Romans,</hi> will be included here alſo, where he ſays, that <hi>theſe things were written for our Learning, that We through Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Comfort of the Scriptures, might have hope.</hi> (Rom. XV. 4.) And here, Bleſſed God! What Conſolations does the Scripture, what rather does it not ſupply us with on theſe Occaſions? What firm Grounds of a ſtedfaſt Confidence in an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and Compaſſionate Father, a Father always able, and always ready to help; a Father, that chaſtiſes becauſe he loves, and only grieves with a Deſign to profit? What Patterns of diſtreſt and injured, and of rewarded and ſucceſsful Virtue does It ſet before our Eyes, and bids us arm our Minds by Their Examples? The Patriarchs, the Prophets, the Apoſtles, but above all, the Meek and Suffering Jeſus! And here, how Glorious a Scene does it draw, what Triumph what Crowns does it propoſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98120:17"/>how raviſhing a Proſpect does it open, by thoſe Aſſurances, that all who ſuffer for and with him, ſhall alſo live and reign with him for ever! The ſweet Tranſports of a Good Conſcience, the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Senſe of a reconciled God, but eſpecially the Experience of his Favour, and the Earneſts and Expectation of a Bleſs'd Eternity; Theſe break in upon Good Men like Light through a Cloud, and are able, if well and warmly applied, to charm all our Griefs, and all our Fears, to calm and ſmooth our very rougheſt Paſſage thro' this Valley of Tears, and to take out the Sting of that laſt greateſt Terrour to poor feeble Men, by ſoftning, nay even recommending Temporal Death it ſelf to us.</p>
            <p>O Welcome therefore Holy Religion to us dark wretched Mortals! Welcome, thou Bleſt, thou Powerful Book, Pure and Clear as the Place from whence thou comeſt, and Wiſe and Good, like Him whoſe Spirit form'd thee. And may, (my Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Brethren) This be ever Firſt and Beſt in our Eſteem, moſt in our Thoughts, our Studies and Deſires: may This be writ entire, and fairly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied not in our Memories only, but our Hearts; and thence ſhine Bright in all our Converſations. And Reaſon good there is, why This Divine Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume ſhould have the Choice of all our Labours; for This will ſanctifie our other Studies, enlarge our Underſtandings, refine and exalt our Souls, and teach us not only to excell Others, but Daily to excell our Selves. This is the only Exception to the Preacher's Character, <hi>In much</hi> of all other <hi>knowledge, there is much ſorrow,</hi> but this makes us wiſe with Pleaſure and Safety; not only wiſer for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98120:18"/>this World, than the reſt of our Learning can, but, which is beſt of all, and a Prerogative peculiar to its ſelf alone, This makes us wiſe for Heaven, and to Salvation.</p>
            <p>All Thanks therefore and due Praiſe be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to our Gracious God, for theſe his Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Praiſe for their General Benefit and Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but double Praiſe for thoſe Advantages, by which we have not only Leiſure, but Obligations and Indiſpenſible Engagements to employ our ſelves in thoſe Holy and Heavenly Studies; Praiſe for the Bounty of thoſe venerable Saints, whoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence hath Dedicated ſo many Souls to God, and made Proviſion for winning over others by their Holy Labours, ſo long as Time ſhall laſt. Praiſe laſtly for the Shine of Their good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who in their ſeveral Stations and Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, have contributed to the Advancement of Learning and Religion; whoſe Names, as well to teſtifie our Gratitude, as to provoke our ſelves and others to Good Works, and the like Labour of Love, it is now my Duty to rehearſe; and may the Recital at this and at all other Times anſwer the Ends of ſo Pious an Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here followed the Commemoration of</hi> BENEFACTORS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory, now and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98120:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
